Andrew Tupper | PhD Biochemistry

☐ +1 (315) 212-7308 • ☑ andrew.s.tupper@gmail.com

Scientist and software engineer. My PhD thesis focused on the developement of computational modeling software to simulate chemical reaction mixtures and the process of RNA replication as it relates to the RNA World hypothesis for the origin of life. As a postdoc, I was employed as a research associate for the United States Department of Agriculture - Agricultural Research Services, where I developed bioinformatic software tools for the detection of plant pathogens using CRISPR-based diagnostics.

Education

McMaster University

PhD Biochemistry and Astrobiology

Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute

BS Interdisciplinary Science - summa cum laude

Hamilton, ON (Canada)

2015-2020

Troy, NY (USA)

2011-2015

Relevant Coursework

- Software Design and Documentation (Capstone)
 Advanced Algorithm Design
- SHARCNET Advanced Research Computing
- o Parallel Programming
- Machine Learning

- Numerical Computing
- Graph Theory
- Data Structures

Research Experience

Horticultural Crops Research Laboratory Research Associate with Dr. Niklaus J. Grijnwald

Corvallis, OR (USA)

2020-2021

- o Population genetics of *P. ramorum*, causal agent of sudden oak death
- Developement of software packages for CRISPR-based diagnostic assays
- System administrator for the 'oomy' compute cluster and web server

McMaster University

Hamilton, ON (Canada)

Graduate Researcher with Dr. Paul G. Higgs

2015-2020

- o Designing computational models of non-enzymatic and enzymatic RNA replication
- Software development of massively parallel programs for high performance computing
- o Lipid-catalyzed polymerization of unactivated RNA monomers in the 'Planet Simulator' Origins lab

Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute

Troy, NY (USA)

Undergraduate Researcher with Dr. James P. Ferris

2012-2013

- Clay-catalyzed polymerization of activated RNA monomers
- o Banin protocol Quantitative ion exchange of clay minerals to simulate prebiotic Earth conditions

Publications

- **Tupper**, A. S. & Higgs, P. G. (2021). Rolling-circle and strand-displacement mechanisms for non-enzymatic rna replication at the time of the origin of life. *Journal of Theoretical Biology*, 110822.
- Cauret, C. M., Gansauge, M.-T., **Tupper**, A. S., Furman, B. L., Knytl, M., Song, X.-Y., . . . Evans, B. J. (2020). Developmental systems drift and the drivers of sex chromosome evolution. *Molecular Biology and Evolution*, *37*(3), 799–810.
- **Tupper**, A. S., Pudritz, R. E., & Higgs, P. G. (2019). Can the RNA world still function without cytidine? *Molecular biology and evolution*.
- Shah, V., de Bouter, J., *Pauli, Q., **Tupper**, A. S., & Higgs, P. G. (2019). Survival of RNA replicators is much easier in protocells than in surface-based, spatial systems. *Life*, *9*(3), 65.
- Pearce, B. K., **Tupper**, A. S., Pudritz, R. E., & Higgs, P. G. (2018). Constraining the time interval for the origin of life on earth. *Astrobiology*, *18*(3), 343–364.
- **Tupper**, A. S. & Higgs, P. G. (2017). Error thresholds for RNA replication in the presence of both point mutations and premature termination errors. *Journal of theoretical biology*, 428, 34–42.
- **Tupper**, A., *Shi, K., & Higgs, P. (2017). The role of templating in the emergence of RNA from the prebiotic chemical mixture. *Life*, 7(4), 41.

Technical and Personal Skills

- o **Programming Languages:** Python, C, C++, R, Bash
- Parallel Languages: openMPI / MPICH, openMP, CUDA, python3-multiprocessing
- Human Languages: English, French (limited)
- Python Libraries: NumPy, SciPy, SKLearn (Machine Learning), PyMC3 (Bayesian)
- o Other Skills: Git, Docker, Conda, Linux, LaTeX

References

Dr. Niklaus J. GrünwaldPostdoctoral Mentor
USDA - ARS
grunwaln@oregonstate.edu
(541) 738-4049

Dr. Paul G. Higgs
PhD Advisor
McMaster University
higgsp@mcmaster.ca
(905) 525-9140 Ext. 26870

Dr. Maikel C. Rheinstädter PhD Supervisory Committee McMaster University rheinsm@mcmaster.ca (905) 525-9140 Ext. 23134

^{*} mentored undergraduate student